<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="document" xml:id="prohd0010">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="main">Sketch of the present State of population, cultivation and
                    produce of Sugars of the Jurisdiction of the Havana with the number of African
                    Slaves imported</title>
                <editor>
                    <persName>
                        <surname>Kraller</surname>
                        <forename>Kathrin </forename>
                    </persName>
                </editor>
                <funder ref="https://www.auswaertiges-amt.de/de/">Auswärtiges Amt</funder>
                <funder ref="https://www.fritz-thyssen-stiftung.de/">Fritz Thyssen Stiftung</funder>
                <funder ref="https://www.gerda-henkel-stiftung.de/">Gerda Henkel Stiftung</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p>Dossier Digital: Alexander von Humboldt y Cuba (1800-1830). ProHD (<date>2021</date>)</p>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</publisher>
                <availability status="free">
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                        (CC BY 4.0)</licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc rend="manuscript">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <institution>Biblioteka Jagiellońska</institution>
                        <collection>Nachl. Alexander von Humboldt</collection>
                        <idno>
                            <idno type="shelfmark">Nachlass Alexander von Humboldt Bd. 3/1 Bl.
                                164-165</idno>
                            <idno type="uri">https://kalliope-verbund.info/DE-611-HS-2878505</idno>
                            <idno type="URLImages">http://jbc.bj.uj.edu.pl/dlibra/publication/367148</idno>
                        </idno>
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation>
                <persName key="ed_ux2_3dq_grb">Woodville, William (1752-1805)</persName>
                <date when="1803">1803</date>
                <placeName>N/A</placeName>
            </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">Englisch</language>
            </langUsage>
            <abstract xml:lang="de">
                <p>Manuskript zum Zusammenhang von Zuckerproduktion und Sklaverei (Stand
                    31.12.1802), sowie Bemerkungen zum Handel mit Sklaven für Havanna. Mit einigen
                    Anmerkungen und Randbemerkungen Humboldts. Mit einigen Anmerkungen und Randbemerkungen Humboldts, sowie der Notiz "PP" am Kopf des ersten Blattes.</p>
            </abstract>
            <abstract xml:lang="es">
                <p>Manuscrito sobre la conexión entre producción de azúcar y esclavitud (31 de
                    diciembre de 1802), así como comentarios sobre la trata de esclavos para La
                    Habana. Con algunas notas y notas marginales de Humboldt. Con algunas anotaciones y notas marginales de Humboldt, así como la nota "PP" en la cabecera de la primera hoja. </p>
            </abstract>
            <textClass>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#notebooks"/>
                <catRef scheme="#form" target="#manuscript"/>
                <catRef scheme="#subject" target="#slavery"/>
                <catRef scheme="#subject" target="#sugar"/>
                <catRef scheme="#subject" target="#plantations"/>
                <catRef scheme="#subject" target="#demography"/>
                <catRef scheme="#genre" target="#essays"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="pb-taxonomy">
                    <category xml:id="genre">
                        <category xml:id="correspondence"/>
                        <category xml:id="diaries"/>
                        <category xml:id="essays"/>
                        <category xml:id="notebooks"/>
                        <category xml:id="travelwriting"/>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="form">
                        <category xml:id="manuscript"/>
                        <category xml:id="print"/>
                    </category>
                    <category xml:id="subjects">
                        <category xml:id="administration"/>
                        <category xml:id="climatology"/>
                        <category xml:id="coffee"/>
                        <category xml:id="colonialism"/>
                        <category xml:id="demography"/>
                        <category xml:id="economicconditions"/>
                        <category xml:id="education"/>
                        <category xml:id="emancipation"/>
                        <category xml:id="factories"/>
                        <category xml:id="geography"/>
                        <category xml:id="medicine"/>
                        <category xml:id="plantations"/>
                        <category xml:id="science"/>
                        <category xml:id="scientificexpedition"/>
                        <category xml:id="sugar"/>
                        <category xml:id="slavery"/>
                        <category xml:id="tobacco"/>
                        <category xml:id="trade"/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <pb n="164r" facs="prohd0010_164r.tif"/>
                <head>Sketch of the present State <metamark place="supralinear"><note place="mTop" hand="#author"> (a) 31.<hi rendition="#sup">st</hi>
                            <choice>
                                <abbr>Dec.<hi rendition="#sup">r</hi></abbr>
                                <expan>December</expan>
                            </choice> 1802</note></metamark> of population, cultivation and produce
                    of Sugars <lb/>of the Jurisdiction of the Havana with the number of African
                    Slaves imported.</head>
                <p>The Island of Cuba, is divided into two Bishoprics and seven Juris<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>dictions, of which that of the Havana is
                    of smallest extent containing only one <lb/>thousand five hundred square
                    Leagues, in which there are eight Cities or Towns <lb/>and fifty <hi rendition="#u">seven<hi rendition="#u"><hi rendition="#u"> </hi></hi><add place="superlinear" hand="#Humboldt, Alexander von">57</add></hi> rural
                    Districts.</p>
                <p>The Cities and Towns contain a population of one hundred &amp; twenty
                    <lb/>thousand Souls, of which there are about one half in the Havana and its
                    Suburbs.</p>
                <p>The rural Districts, are each one under the charge of a Civil Ma<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>gistrate and his Deputy, who preserve
                    Order and administer ordinary Justice <lb/>without armed force; But in many
                    parts, there are no Towns or Vilages to govern.</p>
                <p><add place="left" hand="#Humboldt, Alexander von">14/57</add> Fourteen of these
                    Districts denominated the Thick-<hi rendition="#u">Forrest</hi>, are
                    <lb/>destined to serve as a Ranges of <hi rendition="#u">battle</hi>,
                    comprehending about eight hundred <lb/>square Leagues, with scarely one thousand
                    five hundred White People and about <lb/>an equal number of Slaves.</p>
                <p><add place="left" hand="#Humboldt, Alexander von">30/57</add> Thirty Districts
                    are in Tillage having already three hundred <lb/>and fifty Sugar Estates
                    established, with large Parks for pasturing; Fifty <lb/>Coffee Estates, and a
                    very considerable number of Farms. And there are <lb/>vacant Lands sufficient
                    for the settlement of five or six hundred Sugar<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>Estates more.</p>
                <p>Thirteen Disctricts which remain of the fifty seven, contain the <lb/>Side of
                    Havana, its Suburbs, and Environs: The latter are cultivated <lb/>to supply the
                    City <choice>
                        <abbr>&amp;.<hi rendition="#sup">ca</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>et cetera</expan>
                    </choice> with Vegetables for the Markets, and a prodigious quan<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>tity of Fodder for the vast number of
                    Carriage Horses &amp; Mules kept in it.</p>
                <p>We cannot say, with exactness, what number of free People and <lb/>Slaves are in
                    the forty three Districts first mentioned, but, by an approximate
                    <lb/>calculation, we believe, there may be thirty thousand Slaves on the Sugar
                    <lb/>and Coffee Estates; and on the Farms and other Plantations twenty thousand
                    <lb/>free People of all Collours and fifteen thousand Slaves. <metamark place="inline"><note place="left" hand="#author"> * <hi rendition="#u">in
                                1801.</hi>
                            <lb/><hi rendition="#u">1802.</hi>
                        </note></metamark></p>
                <p>In the course of the Year 1802. Two hundred and four thousand <lb/>four hundred
                    and three Boxes of Sugars, were dispatched at the Custom house <lb/>of the
                    Havana of which, two fifths ought to be Browns and three fifths Whites <lb/>and
                    shoud weigh four hundred Pounds on an Average. Consequently, <lb/>The two fifths
                    Brown, being eighty one thousand, seven hundred Boxes sold <lb/>at six Dollars
                    per Quintal, amount to one Million, nine hundred and sixty thou<lb break="no"/>sand, eight hundred Dollars. And the three fifths Whites, one hundred and
                    <lb/>twenty two thousand, seven hundred and three Boxes at eight Dollars per
                    <lb/>Quintal, Three Millions, nine hundred and twenty six Thousand fourhun<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>dred and ninety Six Dollars. Together
                    with the price paid for the Boxes <lb/>twenty six Reales each will be six
                    hundred &amp; sixty four thousand and, threehundred <lb/><note place="left" hand="#author">and</note><lb/><pb n="164v" facs="prohd0010_164v.tif"/>and nine Dollars. Thus the two
                    hundred and four thousand four hundred <lb/>and three Boxes of Sugars legally
                    shipped at the Havana in 1802 amount <lb/>to Six millions. Five hundred and
                    fifty one Thousand six hundred and <lb/>five Dollars: Nett to the Planters, For,
                    the Exporters paid the Duties, and <lb/>the Mollasses paid amply for the
                    Boxes.</p>
                <p>The produce of the Coffee, Cotton and other Plantations are not <lb/>brought into
                    this account, being yet in an Infant State, nor do we attempt an <lb/>estimation
                    of Sugars illegally exported. We confine this Statement to the regu<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>lar Returns from the Customhouse of the
                    Shipment of Sugars of this Jurisdiction.</p>
                <p>The Money brought hither for maintaining the Fortresses, the <lb/>Marine, Troops
                    and Tobacco Factory. The balance in favour of the <lb/>Havana and against New
                    Spain for bleached Bees Wax. The Cash <lb/>brought from thence by Contraband.
                    The balances against the Floridas<supplied cert="high">,</supplied>
                    <lb/>Louisiana and Porto Rico, form on the whole the Sum of Four Millions
                    <lb/>and Five hundred Thousand Dollars.</p>
                <p>The Products of the Sugars of this Jurisdiction with the Treasure <lb/>annually
                    destined for the purposes before mentioned did asscend in the Year 1802 <lb/>to
                    Eleven Millions and Fifty one Thousand, six hundred and five Dollars.</p>
                <p>We find from the intelligent Planters and Persons well informed <lb/>that we may
                    allow three fourths of the above Sum for Sallaries to White Servants
                    <lb/>Buildings, Mills, Carts, Oxen, Horses, Mules, Repairs &amp; family
                    expences, <lb/>The remaining fourth part. Two Millions, seven hundred Thirty one
                    thousand <lb/>nine hundred and one Dollars, may pay for upwards of nine thousand
                    Slaves <lb/>at three hundred Dollars per head. for the use of Planters &amp;
                    Officers of the King<supplied cert="high">.</supplied><lb/>The Citizens of the
                    Havana, and the other Towns, the Yeomen<choice>
                        <sic>,</sic>
                        <corr type="deleted"/>
                    </choice> &amp; the Husband<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>men <choice>
                        <abbr>&amp;.<hi rendition="#sup">ca</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>et cetera</expan>
                    </choice> may buy one Thousand more. From whence we conclude that, <lb/>Ten
                    Thousands New Negroes may be well Sold and paid for Yearly in this
                    <lb/>Jurisdiction, (and not many more) in Seasons free from Hurricanes or other
                    <lb/>great Calamities.</p>
                <p>The other Jurisdiction, although of very great extent yet being <lb/>little
                    cultivated, may purchase Slaves also, but we cannot give any precise <lb/>Idea
                    of their ability of payment, we therefore leave them out of our calculation
                    <lb/>and suppose them supplied chiefly by Foreign Colonies.</p>
                <p><note place="left" hand="#Humboldt, Alexander von">a</note>The Sugar Planters,
                    purchase few Negresses being unwilling <lb/>to allow them the time requisite
                        <unclear reason="illegible" cert="high">Sying</unclear> in &amp; Nursing
                    their Children. or <lb/>to have the trouble of rearing the Infants; Nor will
                    they allow the Slaves. <lb/>Grounds for Gardens, Live Stock <choice>
                        <abbr>&amp;<hi rendition="#sup">ca</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>et cetera</expan>
                    </choice>. But keep them constantly employed <lb/>in Manufacturing Sugars only.
                    and feed them with dried Salt Beef <lb/>from Buenos Ayres The Main. called
                    Tasajo (Jerked Beef) some Plan<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>ters, but
                    mostly with Ground Provisions purchased from Farmers &amp; <lb/>from the Havana
                    which is imported from Mexico, Campechy, <choice>
                        <abbr>&amp;<hi rendition="#sup">ca</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>et cetera</expan>
                    </choice>.</p>
                <p><pb n="165r" facs="prohd0010_165r.tif"/><note place="left" hand="#Humboldt, Alexander von">b</note>This
                    severe oeconomy is heavily counterpoised by the rapid and <lb/>continual
                    decrease of Slaves; their annu<del rendition="#erased">l</del>al mortallity,
                    cannot be under twelve, to <lb/>fifteen <choice>
                        <abbr>p<choice>
                                <abbr>r</abbr>
                                <expan>er</expan>
                            </choice>Cent.<hi rendition="#sup">m</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>per centum</expan>
                    </choice> and by the want of Creolle Negroes born on the Plantations &amp;
                    <lb/>attached to their Owners, Parent <choice>
                        <abbr>&amp;.<hi rendition="#sup">ca</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>et cetera</expan>
                    </choice> the diminution must be repaired by incessant <lb/>recourse to the
                    purchase of African Slaves.</p>
                <p>In the last 1 Year, 1802, between the first Day of January, and the <lb/>last of
                    December, Thirteen thousand, eight hundred, and thirty two African <lb/><note place="left" hand="#Humboldt, Alexander von">13830</note>Negro Slaves, were
                    imported, and entered at the Customhouse in the Havana. <lb/>out of which, about
                    five hundred were exported; And <add place="superlinear">as</add> the hot
                    Monthly were <lb/>sickly, we do not overrate the mortallity at five <choice>
                        <abbr>p<hi rendition="#sup"><choice>
                                    <abbr>r</abbr>
                                    <expan>er</expan>
                                </choice></hi>Cent</abbr>
                        <expan>per cent</expan>
                    </choice> during the Sales, which <lb/>will be a reduction of seven hundred.
                    Besides, as Newly imported Slaves <lb/>are fully as susceptible of fatal
                    disorders, as seasoned ones, we cannot deduct <add place="superlinear"><hi rendition="#u">for Mortallity</hi></add>
                    <lb/>from the twelve thousand, three hundred and thirty two purchased by the
                    Planters <lb/>less than the same rate. Therefore as the above mentioned whole
                    number, was <lb/>imported successively throughout the Year (perhaps one half in
                    each six Months) <lb/>we will for that reason calculate an half the number at 12 <choice>
                        <abbr>pC.<hi rendition="#sup">t</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>per cent</expan>
                    </choice> which in eight <lb/>hundred Slaves lost in the same Year after their
                    Sale: The result is, that at the <lb/>close of 1802, there was an augmention of
                    about Eleven Thousand and eight hundred <lb/>Negroes to work at the ensuing
                    Crop.</p>
                <p><note place="left" hand="#Humboldt, Alexander von">c</note>It is said, that
                    taking the average of many Plantations, each &amp; every <lb/>Slave employed
                    thereon, will make three Thousand Pounds of Sugar. If it be <lb/>so (and we <add place="superlinear">do</add> believe it to be true) There ought to be Eighty
                    Eight Thousand Boxes of <lb/>Sugars more made in 1803 than the preceding Year.
                    But, we cannot reckon <lb/>on such an increase, by reason of a Drought, which
                    prevailed nine Months in <lb/>part of 1801, and 1802, and checked Vegetation to
                    such a Degree, that the Effects <lb/>are still visible throughout the
                    Colony.</p>
                <p>Strangers are led to suppose this Island blest with better Soil than <lb/>any
                    other in the West Indies; by the great quantity of Sugars, made with so few
                    <lb/>hands . but, when they are informed, that none <hi rendition="#u">but Men
                        Slaves</hi>, are employed <lb/>in its cultivation, and in nothing else; They
                    will perceive, that more is to be <lb/>attributed to the Cruel Oeconomy of the
                    Masters than the fertillity of the <lb/>Land or the favour of the Climate. For,
                    although, both are good the scarcity <lb/>of Running Streams renders Cuba (or at
                    least the Jurisdiction of the Havana) <lb/>less fortunate than Hispaniola.</p>
                <p>Lands are commonly purchased on long Credit, or rather a term for <lb/>payment at
                    the option and convenience of the Purchaser; The value of them <lb/>is fixed and
                    the Buyer pays yearly a Rent, or Tribute after the rate of five <choice>
                        <abbr>pCent</abbr>
                        <expan>per cent</expan>
                    </choice>
                    <lb/>until it suits him to pay off the Principal: The prices vary, in proportion
                    to the <lb/>distance from the Havana; from water carriage, from being windward,
                    <lb/>or leeward, of this Port: and the quality of the Soil, as well as having
                    running <lb/>Waters: insomuch, that the difference may be said to be from twenty
                    to forty <lb/>Dollars <choice>
                        <abbr>p<hi rendition="#sup">r</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>per</expan>
                    </choice> Acre, Brittish (say English) Statute measure.</p>
                <p>
                    <note place="mBottom" hand="#author">This.</note>
                </p>
                <p><pb n="165v" facs="prohd0010_165v.tif"/> This facility of acquiring Lands enables the Planters to invest
                    his <lb/>Capital in Buildings, Machines, Negroes, Cattle <choice>
                        <abbr>&amp;.<hi rendition="#sup">ca</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>et cetera</expan>
                    </choice> and induces many to <lb/>establish new Plantations consequently
                    Produce must increase in proportion<supplied cert="high">.</supplied><lb/>But,
                    at same time it keeps the Planters needy and without ready money to pay <lb/>for
                    a sufficient number of hands for working the Ground to advantage because
                    <lb/>the same facility induces him to undertake to too great extent, and this
                    <lb/>is one great cause of bad payment. But when the Estates shall be
                        disencum<lb break="no"/>bred, and the intercourse with New-Spain free and
                    open. This Colony must <lb/>flourish in a degree unparaleled by any other,
                    without Credit or Assistance <lb/>from the Mother-Country.</p>
                <p>The foregoing Facts clearly exhibit the natural, political and <lb/>adventitious,
                    resources of this Jurisdiction at the present period. And at the <lb/>same time
                    prouves sufficiently that out of the twelve thousand six hundred &amp; upward
                    <lb/>Slaves sold in 1802 more than two thousand, must remain unpaid for, at the
                    <lb/>latter end of the Year.</p>
                <p><note place="left" hand="#Humboldt, Alexander von">d</note>The most favourable
                    time for the importation of Slaves at the <lb/>Havana is from October to the
                    last of January; Ground Provisions then abo<add place="superlinear">und</add>
                    <lb/>and the new Crop of Sugars is approaching or begun<supplied cert="high">.</supplied> But in laying in a <lb/>Cargo for this Place all possible care
                    and circumspection must be taken. <lb/>No aged or ordinary Slaves should be
                    bought. nor many Females although <lb/>Young or handsome. But as many young Men
                    as could by any means <lb/>be procured even tho it were by barterring five
                    Negresses for four Negroes <lb/>or the like. For besides the languishing retail
                    Sales always attendant on <lb/>the disposal of Females, the difference of Price
                    between them and Males is <lb/>from thirty to forty Dollars <choice>
                        <abbr>pr</abbr>
                        <expan>per</expan>
                    </choice> head less, and when the Women are old or ordi<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>nary it is often equal to the prime Cost in Africa. Therefore
                    the purchase <lb/>of Prime young Negroes cannot be too much recommended.</p>
                <p>Foreign Vessel, bringing Slaves, cannot bring with them any, <lb/>other
                    Merchandize whatsoever except the remains of the Cargo carried <lb/>out to
                    purchase Slaves in Africa, or Elephant Teeth, Palm Oil <choice>
                        <abbr>&amp;.<hi rendition="#sup">ca</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>et cetera</expan>
                    </choice> from thence <lb/>and if any such Vessel hath touched at any foreign
                    Portland and barterred or <lb/>sold part of her Slaves, although she may bring
                    the remainder of them she <lb/>may not bring the proceeds of them or any part of
                    them in any kind of the <lb/>Produce of the West Indies on pain of confiscation
                    of Ship &amp; Goods.</p>
                <p>On arrival of this Port every Master must have a written Ma<g ref="#typoHyphen"/><lb break="no"/>nifest ready to deliver to the Governors Adjutant who will
                    board him <lb/>also; in which besides the names of the Vessel and Master, the
                    number of <lb/>Slaves on board, the names and number of Returned Goods, and the
                    number <lb/>of Elephants Teeth, quantity of Bees Wax, Palm Oil <choice>
                        <abbr>&amp;.<hi rendition="#sup">ca</hi></abbr>
                        <expan>et cetera</expan>
                    </choice> must also be inserted<supplied cert="high">.</supplied><lb/>These will
                    be deposited in the King's Stores until the Vessel is ready to <lb/>depart when
                    they will be reshipped without paying any Duty.</p>
                <p>
                    <note place="left" hand="#author">Written Havana 5.<hi rendition="#sup">th</hi>
                        October 1803.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>